<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Learning | Nando @ Aria Media]]></title>
  <link href="http://dnando.github.io/blog/categories/learning/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dnando.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-16T14:24:20+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://dnando.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nando @ Aria Media]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I'm in the Dark Here]]></title>
    <link href="http://dnando.github.io/blog/2014/09/12/im-in-the-dark-here/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-12T00:33:09+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://dnando.github.io/blog/2014/09/12/im-in-the-dark-here</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was watching a <a href="http://youtu.be/Bgaw9qe7DEE?t=48m7s">video of Richard Feynman</a> some time back that inspired me in a very specific way. In it, he talks about his attitude toward not knowing things. Here&rsquo;s a quote from it:</p>

<p>&ldquo;You see, one thing is, I can live with doubt, and uncertainty, and not knowing. I think it&rsquo;s much more interesting to live not knowing than to have answers which might be wrong. I have approximate answers and possible beliefs and different degrees of certainty about different things, but I&rsquo;m not absolutely sure about anything, and there are many things I don&rsquo;t know anything about &hellip; But I don&rsquo;t have to know an answer. I&rsquo;m not frightened by not knowing things.&rdquo;</p>

<p>As a programmer, I&rsquo;m constantly confronted by a cascading, bubbling vortex of all kinds of things I don&rsquo;t know. I don&rsquo;t remember a syntax; my &ldquo;Google Foo&rdquo; is failing me and I can&rsquo;t find an answer; I&rsquo;m not sure of the best way to architect a given process; I&rsquo;m not really clear how a particular business process I&rsquo;m trying to model actually works in the real world; I&rsquo;m only familiar with certain aspects of a language or framework, and the rest lurks in the shadows of what I don&rsquo;t know. In the words of one of my favorite movie scenes &ldquo;I&rsquo;m in the dark here.&rdquo;</p>

<iframe width="853" height="480" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/WZ6p4t3StSc?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>Being in the dark all the time, confronting that ever changing vortex of things I don&rsquo;t know, affects me in various ways. It&rsquo;s an ongoing source of stress. One of my coping mechanisms is to shut down, distract myself, and that leaves me less productive than I could be. It also seems to impact my ability to learn. What impressed me about Feynman is that he seems both enthusiastic, and very clear-headed, about what he does not know. He seems to genuinely enjoy not knowing things, to embrace the state of not knowing. To me, that&rsquo;s a wonderful perspective to cultivate, both as a human being, but particularly as a programmer. It&rsquo;s an inner gestalt that I want to develop.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Redefining How I Learn New Technologies]]></title>
    <link href="http://dnando.github.io/blog/2014/09/11/redefining-how-i-learn-new-technologies/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-11T15:17:20+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://dnando.github.io/blog/2014/09/11/redefining-how-i-learn-new-technologies</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m a programmer. Learning new technologies and techniques is essential to what I do. However, I have noticed lately that learning has become burdened - burdened with time pressure, lots of time pressure; burdened with the sheer volume, diversity and complexity of all the things it seems I <em>must</em> learn to keep up, burdened with the feeling that I am falling ever further behind the hundreds of thousands of brilliant programmers that are constantly pushing our field forward, in every direction, a constantly expanding universe that includes everything from server administration to user interface design to unit / integration testing and a plethora of languages and frameworks that are used to develop web applications. Sum all that up, and to me, learning has become burdened with a fear that I simply won&rsquo;t be able to keep up.</p>

<p>The truth is that I really enjoy learning new things. I feel that&rsquo;s one of the reasons I like programming, why I was attracted to it in the first place. And you know, looking at it clearly, my fear is <em>entirely</em> justified. There is no way in the world for a working programming to keep up with the whole field. It&rsquo;s just too bloody big. And complex. So how can I deal with this situation?</p>

<p>Here is my proposal, to myself. What about taking one <em>small</em> bite at a time? What about simply enjoying the flavor, the taste of learning something new, as it is happening? On a practical basis, I don&rsquo;t have a choice. The field is waayy too big to consume in one go. But on a personal level, I <em>do</em> have a choice.</p>

<p>So this blog is my space for learning new stuff. I&rsquo;ve decided that I&rsquo;m going to redefine my attitude toward learning. Until now, it has seemed that if I&rsquo;m going to keep up, I have to gulp everything down as quickly as possible. Well, that doesn&rsquo;t work. I&rsquo;m left somewhat confused and overwhelmed, and I don&rsquo;t really learn anything, not in a way that I can practically use.</p>

<p>This blog is for taking small bites, chewing things over, and enjoying what I&rsquo;m learning.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
